<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>

<rfc category="std" docName="draft-mauch-grow-anycast-00">
    <front>
        <title>ANYCAST BGP Community for Anycast Routes</title>
        
        <author fullname="Jared Mauch" initials="J." surname="Mauch">
            <organization>Akamai Technologies</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>8285 Reese Lane</street>
                    <city>Ann Arbor</city>
                    <code>48103</code>
                    <country>USA</country>
                </postal>
                <email>jared@akamai.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>

        <author fullname="Job Snijders" initials="J." surname="Snijders">
               <organization abbrev="Fastly">Fastly</organization>
               <address>
                   <postal>
                       <street>Theodorus Majofskistraat 100</street>
                       <code>1065 SZ</code>
                       <city>Amsterdam</city>
                       <country>NL</country>
                   </postal>
                   <email>job@ntt.net</email>
               </address>
          </author>

        <date month="June" year="2022" />

        <abstract>
            <t>
                This document describes the use of a well-known Border Gateway
                Protocol (BGP) community for identifying anycast NLRI in IP networks. This
                well-known advisory transitive BGP community, namely ANYCAST,
                allows an origin AS to specify to a neighboring network
                this route is anycasted.
            </t>
        </abstract>

        <note title="Requirements Language">

            <t>
                The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
                NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
                "OPTIONAL" are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119" />
                only when they appear in all upper case. They may also appear
                in lower or mixed case as English words, without normative
                meaning.
            </t>

        </note>

    </front>

    <middle>
        <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
            <t>
                Network infrastructures have been increasingly seeing anycast
                routes. In order to make traffic engineering easier for partners,
                IP networks have offered BGP communities to signal route attributes.
            </t>

            <t>
                Networks having a global footprint utilize BGP communities to signal
                a variety of attributes, including what prefixes are local, remote,
                customer routes or peers.  Having a method to identify anycasted
                routes is of benefit to determine if there is a desire to have a strong
                affinity to an in city or geography route.
            </t>

            <t>
                BGP and other routing protocols have the ability to adjust the route
                selection to ensure performance, through attributes like weight or local-preference.
                By having a well-known <xref target="RFC1997">BGP
                community</xref> is defined for operational ease will assist operators
                in ensuring they and their partners have the performance they target.
            </t>

            <t>
                Making it considerably easier for network operators to utilize
                such a community makes operations easier.
            </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="attribute" title="ANYCAST Attribute">
            <t>
                This document defines the use of a new well-known BGP transitive community,
                   ANYCAST.
               </t>

               <t>
                   The semantics of this attribute allow a network to interpret
                   the presence of this community as an advisory qualification for
                   any traffic being sent towards this prefix.
               </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="recommendation" title="Operational Recommendations">
            <section anchor="morespecific" title="IP Prefix Announcements with ANYCAST Community Attached">
                <t>
                    When a network originates a route, it SHOULD tag this route with
                    the ANYCAST BGP community.  Operators MAY implement policies 
                    adjusting their internal route scope and selection based on the
                    ANYCAST BGP community.
                </t>
            </section>

        </section>

        <section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
            <t>
                The IANA is requested to register ANYCAST as a well-known BGP community with global significance:
                <list>
                    <t>
                        ANYCAST (= 0xFFFFTBD)
                    </t>
                </list>
            </t>
            <t>
                The low-order two octets in decimal are XXX
            </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
            <t>
                BGP contains no specific mechanism to prevent the unauthorized
                modification of information by the forwarding agent. This
                allows routing information to be modified, removed, or false
                information to be added by forwarding agents.  Recipients of
                routing information are not able to detect this modification.
                Also, <xref target="RFC6810">RPKI</xref> and
                <xref target="I-D.ietf-sidr-bgpsec-overview">BGPSec</xref> do
                not fully resolve this situation. For instance, BGP communities
                can still be added or altered by a forwarding agent even if
                RPKI and BGPSec are in place.
            </t>
            <t>
                The ANYCAST BGP community does not alter this situation.
            </t>

        </section>

        
    </middle>

    <back>

        <references title="Normative References">
           <?rfc include="reference.RFC.1997"?>
           <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
        </references>

        <references title="Informative References">
           <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3882"?>
           <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5635"?>
           <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6810"?>
           <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7454"?>
           <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-sidr-bgpsec-overview"?>
        </references>
        
        <section anchor="acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
            <t>
                The authors would like to gratefully acknowledge many people
                who have contributed discussions and ideas to the making of
                this proposal. They include TBD.
            </t>
        </section>
    </back>

</rfc>
